# ----------------------------------------------- #
# Dialog file for dealing with Other Things       #
# ----------------------------------------------- #

##### Hostile
<HostileIntro>
	I've been instructed not to deal with the likes of you,
	knave.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Bob the Wandering Grobold Minstrel
<BobGreeting>
	Hello, my friend!  Well met, and good day.\n
	\n
	Mayhap you have heard of me ... yes? I am the one they call
	Bob. Bob the singer, Bob the lover. A simple name for the
	greatest of bards, yes? An interesting name, I agree, but of
	course, mine is an interesting and wonderous tale.\n
	\n
	Twenty years ago, as I am sure you know, a great host of Orcs
	plagued these poor towns. Powerful they were, and mighty!
	Farmers, butchers, even poor beggars took up arms that day,
	to protect these homes from the endless ranks of twisted ones.
	I was but a child then, scared and alone, following the tribe
	in search of food and warmth.\n
	\n
	Heroes they were, these men who rose up to drive back that
	wicked host. Think of it! One day to tend your crop or craft
	a rug, the next day to take up sword and shield and fight for
	your home. One such hero was Rogan Tanner, a hunter and
	woodsman. It was him who found me in the woods.\n
	\n
	Of course, no civilized man would think to take me in. But
	Rogan was a man of the woods, and he doted on his wife,
	Aielena. You see Aielena was blind and wanted desperately for
	a child that Rogan could not give her.  For almost a year Rogan
	thought her to be fooled, telling her I was nothing more than
	a lost and orphaned manchild.\n
	\n
	Rogan was, of course, wrong. Aielena was blind, yes, but also
	quite wise in the ways of the world. Nonetheless, a child is
	a child and she loved me as her own ... and for that innocent
	love shall I be eternally grateful. It was Aielena who taught
	me to sing and to speak, and to dance with the grace of a
	gentlemen.\n
	\n
	Shall I sing you a tale? Shall I tell you of the heroes who
	saved this fair land?\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<BobSong>
	Faith. Perseverance. What are these things? Nothing you say?
	Words they are, yes, and words have no substance. Words are
	but spirits, and whispers, and wind ...\n
	\n
	To some, however, these are more than Words ... these are the
	threads which weave our history. I sing you a songs of troubled
	times, of a past shaped of darkness and shadow. I sing you a
	Song of the Heroes who did not falter. They were our light in
	the darkness. They are the holds of faith.\n
	\n
	I sing to you of these Heroes of Legend:\n
	Angus the Grim, Arya and Aryn;\n
	Ash the Ugly, Bloodfiend, and Bone Dancer;\n
	Dennen, Deyth and Div_Devlin.\n
	Duke Rustfield, Durenthal, Elghin, and Envie;\n
	Goodrich, Gradishar, Hades and Haemish.\n
	Halbare and Hedron, J. the Yellow and Kaizen;\n
	Karil, Kasirak, Kirel Redhand, and Krowback,\n
	Nodster, Ransom, Ren Keenblade and Roac.\n
	Sachant, Simeron, Spec, and Tkiam;\n
	Waylandor, Zalaster, and Zisa.\n
	\n
	May their names echo forever in the mountains of this World,
	and may their deeds be whispered until the end of our days.\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Apothecaries
<ApothecaryGreeting>
	Some men deal in weapons, some in armor, I deal in skin and
	teeth, blood and poison, flesh and guts. I have nothing to
	sell you, I fear, but if you bring me pieces of dead monsters,
	I’ve gold in great store with your name on it!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
# Why do you want all this stuff?
<ApothecaryWhy>
	The flesh and bones you bring are not for me, I assure you! I
	am but a humble servant of the Order of Apothecaries. Our
	Learned Master, Revaldo, founded our Order after he parted
	ways with the High Conclave of Wizardry. The Magi of the
	Conclave laughed at Revaldo, and called his theories madness.
	Madness? Ha! Mark my words, once we have changed the shape
	of life on Aerynth and the very face of magic as we know it,
	then it is WE who shall be laughing! Oh yes!\n
	\n
	Revaldo’s theories have yet to produce tangible results, but
	the breakthrough is close at hand! The formulas aren’t quite
	perfected yet, but soon… Soon! In the meantime, my brothers
	must experiment. Our work requires raw materials -- many raw
	materials. Be selective, for not just any wolf fang or
	snakeskin will serve. You shall know suitable pieces when you
	see them -- bring me as much as you can carry!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Lizardman Trainer
<TrainerLizardmanIntro>
	Greetingsss, warm and tasssty one. Thisss one hasss the look
	of war upon them: you would be a ssslayer, yesss? Your ssscalesss,
	taillessss body is inferior, but ssstill, you can be taught,
	I think. I shall teach you many sssecrets of battle, the waysss
	of sssteel, blood, and ssslaughter!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Refiner
<RefinerIntro>
	Welcome. I have been waiting for you. Are you ready to free
	your mind?\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<RefinerSpeech>
	The world around you is illusion: everything you see and hear,
	they are naught but the names your mind gives to them -- by the
	very act of definition your mind limits not what it perceives,
	but rather itself. There is limitless potential within you, but
	the chain of experiences and choices you have made have defined
	you -- they have also limited you. Ironically, your very quest
	for power has denied you the ultimate power locked within your
	soul. I can help.\n
	\n
	I am a Refiner, a humble member of the Order of Transcendence.
	My brotherhood walks a high path of spirituality, and through
	our mastery of Focus we have ascended into new levels of
	awareness. I was once a Warlock, but now I am much more. We
	Refiners have learned how to erase experience, to negate
	perception so that old choices, made long ago, can be made anew.
	As a smith refines ore by boiling away impurities, so I can
	refine and purify your spirit by removing the memory of past
	lessons and errors.\n
	\n
	Your memories are a prison. I can set you free. To reach your
	full potential you must un-learn what you have learned.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Votary
<VotaryIntro>
	Greetings, seeker. I am a Votary, fashioned by the Awakeners
	to serve this sacred Shrine. Render unto me offerings sacred
	to your faith, and I shall serve as a conduit of blessings
	from the Higher Realms!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<VotaryWhatIsThisShrine>
	Listen well to what I say, seeker: the Gods, so long absent
	from this Age of Strife, are returning. Shrines like this one,
	devoted to the Gods of elder Ages, new Gods, or other Powers
	are appearing in cities across the face of Aerynth. I serve
	as Votary of this shrine, its keeper, protector, and mediator.
	This shrine is linked to a great Power beyond the world,
	serving as a conduit of Divine Favor and blessings. Through
	me, you can receive that favor, and feel the touch of cosmic
	power!\n
	\n
	Such blessings do not come without a price. Seek out offerings
	pleasing to the Power this shrine exalts, and bring them here
	to be sacrificed. The shrines that receive the most sacrifices
	will earn the notice and goodwill of their Power, and the
	Votaries of those shrines will then grant Boons to the
	faithful.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089Only a few shrines may be placed in any given city, up to a
	maximum of three. Each shrine favors one race or profession,
	and can only grant boons to that favored race or profession.
	Of all the shrines of a given race or class on the game
	server, only the shrines that have received the most offerings
	will grant powerful boons.\n
	\n
	To sacrifice an offering, double-click the offering object
	then select the shrine.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<VotaryHowDoesDFAffectMe>
	I, the Votary of this shrine, am empowered to grant Boons of
	Divine Favor to those favored by the shrine's exalted Power,
	if there have been sufficient offerings. Any may sacrifice an
	offering to the shrine, but only those favored by its Power
	may receive a boon. Only those bound to the Tree of Life that
	safeguards this shrine may partake of Boons from me, its
	Votary. If you are favored, ask me for a boon and it shall be
	granted! The touch of Divine Favor shall grant a blessing
	that shall last for some time.\n
	\n
	Know this: the Powers are testing their faithful, and only the
	strongest shall know their goodwill. The Powers favor Guilds
	that are masters of their own destiny, and prefer fresh
	offerings! The faithful must strive to win the favor of their
	chosen Powers: only those shrines that have rendered the most
	offerings to their Power will grant true Boons.\n
	\n
	Know also that the Powers do not look kindly on those who
	abuse their favor: each Boon granted will reduce the shrine's
	favor, and the faithful must continually sacrifice new
	offerings to their shrines, lest their Power lose interest in
	their works.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089Each offering sacrificed to a shrine has a favor rating. When
	sacrificed, the favor rating of the offering is added to the
	total favor rating of the shrine. A shrine's favor rating
	decreases over time, and each time its Votary grants a Boon.\n
	\n
	Each shrine has a specific Boon effect that its Votary can
	bestow only upon members of its favored race or profession who
	belong to the Guild that owns the city the shrine is placed
	in.\n
	\n
	The effectiveness of a shrine’s Boons depends on several
	factors, including:\n
	Guild Status -- only Sovereign Guilds receive the full Boon
	bonus. Sub-guilds or sworn guilds have their Boons reduced in
	power.\n
	Shrine Favor -- only the shrine on the server with the highest
	favor rating grants the Boon at full effectiveness. The shrine
	with the second-highest favor rating grants the Boon at less
	strength, and all other shrines grant only tiny proportions
	of the full Boon bonus, if any. Remember that both the
	granting of Boons and the passage of time can reduce a shrine's
	favor rating, possibly limiting the effects of its Boons.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<VotaryWhereToFindOfferings>
	There are many things pleasing to each God or Power -- seek
	their legendary enemies, or else look for lost, precious
	things revered by their faith. Some offerings will be
	favorable to many shrines, others to only one. Every shrine
	will accept many different types of offerings, scattered in
	different regions. Seek offerings through quest, but beware,
	once an offering has been found, it may easily be stolen by
	the unscrupulous ...\n
	\n
	There is another way to seek the favor of the Gods. When an
	offering is sacrificed to a shrine, it is miraculously
	transformed into an elan stone, a sacred object of immense
	power. Any shrine will accept these stones as offerings. A
	shrine's cache of elan stones may be plundered, but only if
	that shrine is destroyed. To destroy a shrine, weaken the
	Tree of Life that sustains that shrine through siege. Thus
	Faith must be wed to Might in the wars of the Upstart Gods.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089Favor offerings are available as loot items in
	specific zones. Mouse over an offering for a list of the
	shrines that will accept that offering, as well as the amount
	of favor the offering will earn for each shrine.\n
	\n
	A shrine's accumulated favor can be looted, in the form of
	elan stones, if the shrine is destroyed. To destroy a shrine,
	de-rank the Tree of Life for that shrine's city.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<VotaryWhoCanGetBoons>
	Know this: each shrine is devoted to a Power, and I may only
	bestow boons upon those favored by that Power, be they scions
	of one race or walkers of one path.\n
	\n
	Know also that the Tree of Life in this City serves as the
	conduit from the Higher Realms to this world. Only those whose
	souls are bound to the Tree that nourishes this shrine may
	receive Divine Favor from it.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089Each shrine is devoted to a specific race or profession, and
	can only grant Boons to that kind of character. Only members
	of the Guild that owns the shrine can receive Boons.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Blood Mage
<BloodMageGreeting>
	Welcome. I have been waiting for you. Are you ready to embrace
	the destiny locked within your blood?
<CHAPTEREND>
<BloodMageSpeech>
	It is one thing to free the mind, but if the flesh is still
	locked in the shackles of ignorance, there is still no
	victory. The Order of Transcendence has sent me, to help you
	unlock the hidden potential that lies locked within your
	blood. The highest of the Gods' children, Humans and Elves,
	were wrought long ago into distinct kindreds, bloodlines each
	blessed with their own unique talents and glories. Alas, the
	tides of history have muddied those bloodlines, so that few
	of truly pure blood remain. But know this: the glimmers of
	heritage still wait, dormant, within every Firstborn or Son
	of Men. I can awaken them.\n
	\n
	I am a Blood Mage, a humble member of the Order of
	Transcendence. My brotherhood walks a high path of
	spirituality, and through our mastery of Focus we have
	ascended into new levels of awareness. I was once a Warlock,
	but now I am much more. We Blood Magi have learned how to
	reach beyond awareness and the memory of the mind to the
	memory held within the blood, the ancient vessels of
	heredity. As a smith refines ore by boiling away impurities,
	so I can refine and purify your blood by unlocking the traits
	of distant ancestors and awakening the true power of your
	bloodline.\n
	\n
	Your flesh is imprisoned, ignorant of the greatness that once
	flowed in its blood, untold generations ago. Do you have the
	courage to release your body, and embrace the legacy of your
	bloodline?
<CHAPTEREND>

# Seneschal
<SeneschalGreeting>
	Need you the fruits of the guild's mines?  I can show you
	what the workers have gathered.\n
<CHAPTEREND>
# Tell me more about Resources and mines.
<SeneschalTellMeMore>
	Of course, good sir! This Warehouse is the key through which
	this City may tap into the mineral wealth of Aerynth, using
	it to prosper. I can help manage this city, maintaining it in
	this uncertain age.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
# How can this warehouse help manage this city?
<SeneschalCityManagement>
	As Seneschal, it is my duty to see that the City runs
	smoothly, and is well maintained. All Fortress Assets (city
	walls, and barracks) and any building protected by the
	Runemaster will, if its strongbox be empty, draw its
	maintenance fees from the store of gold in this Warehouse.
	Thus, the masters of this City need no longer worry about
	rushing from wall to wall, ensuring that they are maintained
	-- I can oversee those efforts from now on.\n
	\n
	Of course, for me to do my duties, there needs be gold in the
	Warehouse, gold in great store. It is up to you to put it
	here!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
# How can I put Gold in this Warehouse?
<SeneschalGold>
	Anyone may deposit gold in this Warehouse, which I shall keep
	safe until it is needed to pay out maintenance on the walls,
	barracks, and other protected structures. The efforts of any
	citizen may now easily be directed to the good of the City.\n
	\n
	The easiest way to fill this Warehouse with wealth, however,
	is to claim a Gold Mine. The ancient mines have been
	uncovered, in the adventurous lands where fell beasts lurk.
	If your City should claim a mine and hold it, gold shall be
	brought into the Warehouse every hour. The amount of gold a
	mine produces decreases the farther way a claimed mine is from
	this Warehouse (the porters must be paid, after all), but the
	masters of a mine can increase its output by appointing
	Harvesters to work at the mine.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
# Can gold be removed from this Warehouse?
<SeneschalGoldRemoval>
	Other than the automatic removal of funds to help maintain
	this city’s fortress and protected assets, there are two ways
	gold may be withdrawn from this Warehouse.\n
	\n
	The leaders of the city, that is to say, the Guild Leader and
	all members of the Inner Council, may withdraw funds to use at
	their discretion. But know this: there are limits to this
	privilege! Custom demands that I keep a large minimum sum
	within the warehouse, to ensure city maintenance in the event
	of troubles. Should the city leadership attempt to withdraw
	funds that would take the Warehouse stores below this minimum,
	or if the stores are less than the minimum to begin with, any
	cash withdrawal shall be forbidden. If you would use this
	Warehouse as a steady source of gold, keep its coffers full!\n
	\n
	The second means of taking gold is much less wholesome. Should
	this warehouse be destroyed in time of siege, its contents
	shall lie loose in the wreckage to be plundered. Alas, our
	world has ever been a harsh one. To the victors go the spoils.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
# How can I claim or defend resource mine?
<SeneschalMine>
	Every resource mine is invulnerable for much of the day. There
	is, however, a brief span when they may be claimed by any
	Prospector who awakens the mine. Look to your world map -- it
	will show which mines are vulnerable, who has claimed them,
	and also gives the time that their window of opportunity shall
	open.\n
	\n
	Once a mine becomes vulnerable, any who would claim it must
	first destroy the Tower that guards the mine. The mine may
	have guards to help defend it. Once the defenses are broken,
	a Prospector must brace himself in a prospecting stance, then
	claim it. This process takes time, during which that
	Prospector must be well defended!\n
	\n
	If the Prospector should claim the mine, the fight is still
	not yet over -- any other Prospector may come along to
	overwrite the claim, so long as the mine is vulnerable. Only
	the LAST Guild to claim the mine shall own it, once the window
	of opportunity closes. Messages shall be sent whenever a mine
	is claimed -- watch them carefully, and be ready to act
	quickly should your claim be opposed. When the window of
	opportunity closes, if your Guild's claim was the last, your
	emblems shall display on the new guard tower and the world
	map, and the flow of gold to this Warehouse shall begin.\n
	\n
	The leaders of a nation may change when a mine’s window of
	opportunity opens, but any change they make shall carry forth
	to all mines that nation claims. Choose carefully, for all of
	your mines shall always become vulnerable at the same instant!\n
	\n
	You can help defend the mine by improving the Guard Tower,
	raising its rank as can be done with other buildings. Also,
	you may assign Guards to the mine to help protect the
	Harvesters and defend it during its vulnerable time.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
# Are the other resources besides gold?
<SeneschalOtherResources>
	In ages past the Dwarves and Empires of old delved for all
	manner of precious stones and ores, quarried the face of
	mountains, wove mana from the ley lines, and consumed the
	forests with their need for lumber. So far the Prospectors
	have only managed to awaken the gold mines of yore, but they
	are searching for the other ancient mines and timber sources
	as we speak. The devastation of the Turning so far keeps them
	hidden, but in time the old mines may open again! Once that
	happy day comes, I shall keep all manner of precious things
	in this Warehouse, not just gold.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>


# Hermit of Power
<PowerHermitIntro>
	Who is this I see before me? What business does one of the
	living have in the lands of the Dead? If you seek death, you
	shall not find it here, not until the Lich Queen finally wins
	and casts all creation into darkness. If you seek wealth or
	greatness I have none to give you. Do you seek power, the
	power to rule? Here perhaps I can help you. If you would be
	a king, you must learn what power is, and where it lies.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<PowerHermitSpeech>
	You do not recognize my face, ruined by the scourge of time
	and rot. Nor should you -- when I died, the first day had yet
	to dawn, and Time itself was not even a dream. To know me,
	look to the statue outside. When Twilight still blanketed
	creation and the stars still ruled the sky, I was called
	Sillestor. I was a king, one of the mightiest this world has
	ever seen. Looks upon my works, ye mighty, and despair! Now?
	Now I am naught but bones, and dust, and memory.\n
	\n
	When I drew breath I was mighty indeed, one of the firstborn
	of the Sidhe, tutored by the Gods themselves in Gilliandor's
	Twilight Kingdom. I raised arms against the Dragon, and after
	the Gods themselves did battle with it, it was I who doubted
	the words of the All-Father, and questioned their victory. It
	was for me that Thurin forged the Sword of Destiny, at my
	request. It was I who named it: Shadowbane. All the world has
	known that name, and dreaded it.\n
	\n
	To me Thurin gave his mighty gift, and with it came power. I
	looked upon the chaos and dissention of the Dragon's wake,
	and brought all to order. I forged the Deathless Empire, with
	Shadowbane in my hand. I wrought pacts with the Elemental
	Princes, the Beast Lords, and the Demon Lordlings in the Pits
	of Chaos. The Sidhe heeded my counsel, and obeyed my
	commandment. All the world's princes knelt before me, in that
	age before Man was ever wrought. Power, limitless power, was
	mine. With steel and sorcery, I showed my people that we
	could become as Gods ourselves. Look at me now. What a God I
	have become ...\n
	\n
	It was not until I turned the wrath of my empire from demons
	or scaly horrors to the Centaurs, the other children of the
	Gods that shared the twilight with us, that I learned a
	mighty lesson, upon the edge of Shadowbane itself. You have
	no doubt heard legends of the Taming. I raised my sword
	against Pandarrion Himself, and his servant Thurin, who gave
	me the gift of Shadowbane, the gift of power, took it away.
	And my life with it. As I died I learned the highest truth:
	Power in and of itself is nothing. Those who would hold
	dominion over others must temper their power with wisdom, and
	with fortune. In the end, there is always someone with more
	power, even than an emperor. Power destroys only those who
	never truly have it.  Listen to me, and heed my warning.\n
	\n
	My foolish grandchild, in her greed, raised my bones from
	death with dark necromancy to take counsel and arcane secrets
	from me. I tried to teach her my lesson, but she would not
	hear it. She wanted only the blade. She took it, seized power
	through betrayal, but was herself betrayed. Now she is the
	Lich Queen, mistress of Oblivion, and hordes of living dead
	and vampires serve her will. Yet even now her power is but an
	illusion. She is no queen, she is but a pawn, a puppet
	dancing on the ebon strings of the Null, that dread power
	which waits outside, and hungers.\n
	\n
	Now the Gods have spoken to me, from beyond, and told me that
	solitude and eternal shame are to be my punishment. They have
	also entrusted me, power's pawn, with their blessing. I can
	grant unto you the blessing of Power, if you are worthy. But
	know this: if you would rule a realm, power alone will not be
	enough.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<PowerHermitKing>
	Gods make kings -- not crowns, or armies, or palaces. To gain
	dominion over a realm you need a Palace. To build a Palace,
	you will need a full-grown Tree of Life, many followers, gold
	and resources in great store, and a Charter. To enact that
	Charter, you will need the favor of the Gods. You must walk
	the King's Path humbly, around the world and back again, and
	return home for a boon at a Shrine with three Blessings upon
	you.\n
	\n
	There are three Hermits, dwelling in the far corners of the
	world. Seek them out, and from them gain the Blessings of
	Power, Fortune, and Wisdom. But beware: just as rule is a
	burden, so are these Blessings. They will slow your pace,
	deny you easy travel, and draw your enemies. You must walk
	the King's Path as quickly as you can, to all three hermits
	and home again without any aid but Runegates. If you die on
	the path, or if a blessing should expire before you return
	home again, your quest has failed. Your enemies will know you
	seek a throne, and may try to stop you. If you are served by
	loyal followers, and if Wisdom, Power, and Fortune favor you,
	you shall run your race well, to the end.\n
	\n
	Once you have attained all three blessings, return to your
	city and use your Charter. Your Tree shall be reborn as a
	palace, and your dominion over a new realm will begin.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>


# Hermit of Fortune
<FortuneHermitIntro>
	What have we here? A traveler. Are you seeing the sights?
	Have you come to this blasted isle for revenge? For wealth?
	For power? Or perhaps you have a higher goal ... Do you seek
	dominion? If ever you would rule a realm, you must talk to
	me, and hear the lesson I would impart to you. I can make you
	a king, if your luck holds.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<FortuneHermitSpeech>
	I? Voldrok is my name, the name I took when the touch of
	Chaos transformed me and gave me new birth. I am but a humble
	servant, the lackey of a mighty lord. One he was a God, one
	of the Seven who first wrought the world. Now he is a pawn of
	fate, an imp of Chaos. There is his statue. Morloch is his
	name now, though he has known another. I will not speak it.\n
	\n
	Look well upon the image of my master. Here you see a God,
	cunning, mighty, strong beyond all measure. And yet he has
	lost everything. Once the fairest of the Gods, now he hides
	his ruined face behind a mask. Once best-loved, he mourns his
	fallen wife, and knows the hatred of every race that lives.
	Once the god of war and battles, he has lost every war he
	fought, and the greatest weapon ever forged has eluded his
	grasp, though he has fought three times to win it. How can
	this be? Why is one so mighty so humbled?\n
	\n
	The answer is simple: Fortune. All our lives are driven by
	the whims of cruel fate. It is as if we are, all of us,
	chained to a mighty wheel. As that wheel turns, those who
	stand atop it are cast down, to be ground under it. Morloch
	has ever cursed his fate: the Dragonfire that maimed him and
	took away his bride, the ill chances that thwarted his
	schemes to rule the Giants and the Dwarves, the blind luck
	that saved the All-father from the trap he set in the Pits of
	Chaos, and the missteps that kept all ten fragments of the
	Gleaming Stone from his grasp. Again and again, Fortune has
	robbed him of victory. Fate. Luck. But for them, Morloch would
	be the greatest king of all. Will you do better?\n
	\n
	I have served Morloch long, since before he took that name.
	Once I was a loyal soldier among the Vorgrim, trained to do
	battle by the War God himself. I was there, in the Pits of
	Chaos, when the trap my Lord wrought to kill the All-Father
	unraveled. All by brothers were tainted by Chaos, becoming
	the Twisted Breeds. But not I. I was reborn not as man, or
	demon, but as something else. I was chosen for a higher
	purpose.\n
	\n
	I have served Morloch ever since as his emissary, his high
	priest. I have brought legions to his cause, and spread fear
	among his enemies. I have journeyed to every fragment, seen
	uncounted lands, fought uncounted foes. I helped my lord in
	his quest for the Gleaming Stone, last of Volliandra's relics.
	But by the end of that quest I had learned something,
	something Morloch has never understood. Any who would rule
	need fortune: luck must smile upon them if their rule is to
	last. But true kings are not fortune's slaves: they are its
	masters, making their own luck and bending events to their
	will. I tried to explain this to my lord. He would not hear
	my words, and cast me from his service. Only the essence of
	this blighted age kept me from death, for none of us may
	truly die. As I wandered here, near the gate where I left
	Aerynth once and returned, I heard new voices.\n
	\n
	The Gods have called to me, from far away. They told me that
	I have grasped one of the keys to kingship, and that my
	understanding has made me fortune's keeper. I can dole out
	fortune's blessing to any that seek to rule a realm, and let
	them run their race to a throne. Would you take it? If you
	do, always remember: you need luck in abundance to rule, but
	fortune's favor is not so fickle as it seems. The best luck
	is the luck YOU make, for yourself.  Will you be a king? Will
	fortune smile upon you?\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<FortuneHermitKing>
	Gods make kings -- not crowns, or armies, or palaces. To gain
	dominion over a realm you need a Palace. To build a Palace,
	you will need a full-grown Tree of Life, many followers, gold
	and resources in great store, and a Charter. To enact that
	Charter, you will need the favor of the Gods. You must walk
	the King's Path humbly, around the world and back again, and
	return home for a boon at a Shrine with three Blessings upon
	you.\n
	\n
	There are three Hermits, dwelling in the far corners of the
	world. Seek them out, and from them gain the Blessings of
	Fortune, Wisdom, and Power. But beware: just as rule is a
	burden, so are these Blessings. They will slow your pace,
	deny you easy travel, and draw your enemies. You must walk
	the King's Path as quickly as you can, to all three hermits
	and home again without any aid but Runegates. If you die on
	the path, or if a blessing should expire before you return
	home again, your quest has failed. Your enemies will know you
	seek a throne, and may try to stop you. If you are served by
	loyal followers, and if Wisdom, Power, and Fortune favor you,
	you shall run your race well, to the end.\n
	\n
	Once you have attained all three blessings, return to your
	city and use your Charter. Your Tree shall be reborn as a
	palace, and your dominion over a new realm will begin.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hermit of Wisdom
<WisdomHermitIntro>
	So you have found me. Do you seek a crown? Go away then, for
	I have none to give you. Crowns mean nothing: they do not
	make a king. Only the Gods can make a king. You seek to rule?
	Your road will be long, and again, I have little to offer you.
	Only a lesson, and a blessing if you're worthy. They will give
	you but a start. Heed my lesson and use the blessing well,
	and you may yet come to rule. The world needs rulers now, more
	than ever. Bloody anarchy has reigned too long ...\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<WisdomHermitSpeech>
	I? My name is unimportant, easily forgotten. I have no need
	of it anymore. Once I served a king. A great king, the
	greatest the Sons of Men have ever known. He was chosen by
	the All-Father, blessed by the Archons. In his prime, he had
	everything a king could need: a realm at peace, vassals who
	loved him, and the power to bring justice and virtue to the
	realms of men. I was his right hand, his champion. I fought
	his wars, vanquished his enemies, saved his life. I gave him
	the means to fulfill his greatest dream.\n
	\n
	Where is he now? Lost. Dead. A hundred years dead. Look at
	the statue outside and you shall see his likeness. I cannot
	speak his name. I am no longer worthy. He was undone.\n
	\n
	I failed him. Gods forgive me, I saw him die. I failed my
	king in the hour of greatest need. And so that great king
	died, and all the world was ruined. Why was he undone? The
	king had power and fortune, virtue and wealth, he had a will
	that earned the respect even of his enemies and a bearing so
	blessed that entire nations would die for him. He had a
	legion of Champions, and an ageless Wizard to aid him. He
	even held Shadowbane, the blade of Destiny. He had all this,
	yet he was still undone. How? Why?\n
	\n
	It was folly that brought him down. The folly of his
	ancestors had doomed his race to bitter enmity with the
	Elves, and in the face of Elvish slights his pride moved him
	to war. And as the War of Tears raged, my king fought hard,
	even to the brink of ruin. Fortune brought him Power, the
	power of Shadowbane itself, and his realm was saved. But
	there was one thing my king lacked. Wisdom. He embraced the
	folly of his ancestors, and made vengeance a virtue, driven
	on by Champions who could not see past hatred. It was not
	enough to defeat our enemy, they said. The Elves must be
	utterly destroyed. And so it nearly was. In his arrogance, my
	king sought to undo the work of the Gods themselves, and
	remove their eldest children from the face of Aerynth. I
	watched all this, and did nothing. Even when my heart was
	moved to rage by what I saw in the broken cities of the enemy,
	I did nothing. When the Archons spoke to me from on high, and
	warned me of the Doom my king would wreak upon the world, I
	did nothing. Gods save me, I would not always do nothing ...\n
	\n
	The king's pride was finally his undoing, and he was killed.
	I failed my king. I saw him die. I let it happen, even when
	I had the power to stop it. And so the earth trembled, and
	the skies wept blood, and the globe of the world shattered.\n
	\n
	I fled all the lands I knew, and went into the wastes,
	wanting only to die. But like all of us in this shadowed age,
	I am cursed to live. I made my way here, to these forlorn
	wastes, to raise a statue of my fallen king among the ruins
	of Ardan, where reigned the first king among the Sons of Men.
	And I have heard the voices of the Gods and Archons again.
	Again they have touched my soul, and blessed me. For the
	Wisdom that I had my king was taken by folly, I have been
	made Wisdom's keeper. I can give the Blessing of Wisdom to
	all who are worthy. They, in turn, will build new palaces,
	and this world shall know kings and crowns again. But I care
	little for all that. I have betrayed my king, and no
	forgiveness or Blessing shall ever wash the grief from my
	soul.\n
	\n
	Would you be a king? Take my hollow blessing, then. Use it
	well. May you find the Wisdom that eluded my lord and master.
	May you and your brother monarchs fashion order out of
	lawlessness. May you reign in peace.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>
<WisdomHermitKing>
	Gods make kings -- not crowns, or armies, or palaces. To gain
	dominion over a realm you need a Palace. To build a Palace,
	you will need a full-grown Tree of Life, many followers, gold
	and resources in great store, and a Charter. To enact that
	Charter, you will need the favor of the Gods. You must walk
	the King's Path humbly, around the world and back again, and
	return home for a boon at a Shrine with three Blessings upon
	you.\n
	\n
	There are three Hermits, dwelling in the far corners of the
	world. Seek them out, and from them gain the Blessings of
	Wisdom, Power, and Fortune. But beware: just as rule is a
	burden, so are these Blessings. They will slow your pace,
	deny you easy travel, and draw your enemies. You must walk
	the King's Path as quickly as you can, to all three hermits
	and home again without any aid but Runegates. If you die on
	the path, or if a blessing should expire before you return
	home again, your quest has failed. Your enemies will know you
	seek a throne, and may try to stop you. If you are served by
	loyal followers, and if Wisdom, Power, and Fortune favor you,
	you shall run your race well, to the end.\n
	\n
	Once you have attained all three blessings, return to your
	city and use your Charter. Your Tree shall be reborn as a
	palace, and your dominion over a new realm will begin.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>