# ----------------------------------------- #
# Dialog file for dealing with Runemaster   #
# ----------------------------------------- #

######## All
<HostileIntro>
	Do not expect any help from me, vagabond. You should go to
	the continent, for this peaceful island is not the place for
	the likes of you.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# What else can you tell me?
<RunemasterWhatElse>
	I've lived here long, and there's much more I can tell you
	of nearby lands ...\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

######## City Intros

# Knightsbridge
<City_KnightsbridgeIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to the City of Knightsbridge. I am Elbuerin,
	Runemaster and keeper of the Tree. This city was once ruled
	by the tyrant Garridal Truesteel, but his son has since taken
	up the path of virtue. Knightsbridge has endured famine,
	Turning, and plagues of Orcs, but still it stands. The times
	grow troubled, however. Our city has more need of heroes now
	than ever.\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Silverlance
<City_SilverlanceIntro>
	Welcome to Silverlance Keep! Yalerian is my name, and I serve
	as Runemaster here. Sixty years after the Turning, a large
	army of Centaurs arrived on Tyrranth Minor through a Runegate,
	and built this city to serve as a fortress of order and good.
	Their efforts brought peace and stability to Tyrranth Minor,
	but now even the Horselords are troubled, and I fear we shall
	have need of new heroes if this city is to survive.\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Swampstone
<City_SwampstoneIntro>
	Hail, traveler. I am Edruin, Runemaster of this city. If
	you would begin a Guild or leave these wretched lands to
	seek fortune on the mainland, I can aid thee.\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	swamps are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The woods are teeming with
	grobolds and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Wanford Castle (Dalgoth)
<City_WanfordIntro>
	Greetings, traveler. You have come to Wanford Castle, bastion
	of the Holy Church and protector of these lands. Here was
	writ the great Creed that bound the wayward faiths of Men,
	Elves, and Horselords into one mighty Church. The light they
	kindled so long ago still shines against the darkness. Be at
	peace here -- rest yourself, seek out arms and supplies, or
	better yourself through instruction and prayer. The bishop
	has ordained that all who combat the forces of Chaos and
	Darkness shall be welcome in these walls.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Lion's Gate (Dalgoth)
<City_LionsGateIntro>
	Hail to thee, and well met! You've come to Lion's Gate, named
	for Cambruin himself, the Golden Lion who united the Ten
	Kingdoms of Men. A little more than a century ago, the High
	King rode at the head of his armies to defend the Patriarch
	in Dalgoth from the Barbarian hordes to the north. He
	scattered his foes, and left the city to stand as a bastion
	against strife. Here the High King's memory still lives, and
	we work to revive his glory as best we may. The Turning has
	brought all manner of folk here, and the streets have grown
	rowdy indeed.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Therikos Senn (Dalgoth)
<City_TherikosSennIntro>
	Be welcome, stranger, to Therikos Senn! Sixty years after the
	Turning, a large army of Centaurs arrived in these lands
	through a Runegate, racing to the aid of the Patriarch in
	Dalgoth. Long staunch supporters of the holy Church, they
	built this city to serve as a fortress of order and good.
	Their efforts brought peace and stability to the Holy See,
	but now even the Horselords are troubled, for all the lands
	beyond are filled with strife and foul things. I fear we
	shall have need of new heroes if this city is to survive.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Dalgoth (Dalgoth)
<City_DalgothIntro>
	May the peace and grace of the Holy Saints and Blessed Archons
	be upon you. You stand now in the Holy City, Dalgoth the
	Great, built thousands of years ago on the very ground where
	the Archons blessed the Sons of Men, and guided them out of
	bondage and slavery. Here sits the Nestor the Twenty-sixth,
	the Blessed Patriarch, steward of the All-Father's Holy
	Church. All who walk the paths of virtue and faith are
	welcome here, for they shall find faith, aid, and fulfillment.
	Those who seek only worldly power should look elsewhere.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Bastion (Maelstrom)
<City_BastionIntro>
	The Order of Sentinels bids you welcome to Bastion. You've come
	here none too soon. Of the dozen watch forts that once ringed
	the Chaos Gate, this is the last. The rest have fallen, swept
	away by the demonic hordes that are now moving through the
	Chaos Gate. The Gate itself lies north of here, past the
	battleground where the eleventh fortress once stood. The Lord
	General has decreed that all who do battle with demons are
	welcome in Bastion, and all who fight Chaos do so with the
	blessings of the All-Father. Rest yourself, buy what provisions
	you need, then go forth to battle!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Perdition (Maelstrom)
<City_PerditionIntro>
	You have come unto Perdition, stranger! Here the True Gods are
	worshipped, and the Old Gods who have failed this world have
	been cast down. A new age is dawning, an age of Chaos, and this
	is the first manifestation of its coming. Look upon our glorious
	Tree, refined and perfected by the touch of Chaos! Rest, learn,
	and worship the Dark Lords with us. We seek to build a new life
	here, and eagerly await the day when the Dark Lords will return
	and reward our faith. Do as you will, for that is the only law
	we venerate here!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Starkholm (Vorringia)
<City_StarkholmIntro>
	Look upon Starkholm, center of Uthgaard, and be welcome!
	Three hundred summers ago, the hero Stark Skullbreaker and
	his kin raised this mighty city, which endured even the
	Turning. Now we face new perils as fell things stir to the
	northeast. Seek ye arms here near the Tree, or cross the
	river to find training in the hold. When you are ready, go
	into the hills and mountains to the northeast, where the Dark
	Folk wait to feel the vengeance of the Northman! May Torvald
	look upon your deeds!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Erkeng Hold (Vorringia)
<City_ErkengHoldIntro>
	You stand in Erkeng Hold, stranger! All who bring no strife
	with them are welcome here. In the time of Hjallmar's great
	war between the Invorri tribes against the Ten Kingdoms,
	Northman chieftain Egil Skullbreaker founded Erkeng as a
	rearguard stronghold against the Jotun and beast-kin. Wars
	and strife have swept away too many of the old strongholds,
	but Erkeng still stands, giving sanctuary from the bite of
	winter and the blades of fell beasts.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Aeldreth (Vorringia)
<City_AeldrethIntro>
	Be at peace, traveler, for you have come to Aeldreth. After
	the kingdom of Vanderlund fell victim to its dark doom, the
	Druids of this land emerged from hiding to tend to the
	stricken people. We forged a sanctuary here for all amidst
	the growing shadows. In honor of Braialla, our community was
	made in complete harmony with the natural world. Aeldreth is
	still a young city, but we stand defiant against the harsh
	Children of the North and the terrors of this dark Age.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Sea Dog's Rest (all)
<City_SeaDogsRestIntro>
	Ahoy, stranger! You've found our refuge -- this was once the
	favored bolt hole of none other than Verdan Hoag, the Sea Dog,
	fiercest pirate to ever plow the seas of Aerynth! Alas, the
	fleets and armada of ages past are all gone now, either lying
	in Lashava's Bower or else reduced to kindling on the strands.
	Verdan himself died here, victim of an Elvish curse. But we,
	the descendents of his faithful crew, remained, and have built
	a haven here for scoundrels, refugees, and all others who
	Fortune has treated harshly. So be ye welcome! Keep the peace,
	and ye can stay as long as ye like.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

######## Hamlet Intros

# Blantris
<Hamlet_BlantrisIntro>
	You've come to Blantris, wayward traveler. I serve here as
	the Runemaster, wise in lore. Blantris was the oldest son of
	Berren, the great Lord who first settled Tyrranth Minor in the
	name of Ethyria. Blantris died here, slain by the savage
	Lizardmen tribesmen who dwell in these marshes. Berren's
	long war for vengeance began here, long ago. The might of the
	Scaly Ones was broken, but now new enemies face us, and the
	times are dark ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	swamps are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The woods are teeming with
	grobolds and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Kilrayden
<Hamlet_KilraydenIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to Kilrayden Village. I am the Runemaster
	of this settlement. After the Turning, refugees from distant
	lands settled here, after the lords of Knight's Bridge and
	Silverlance denied them. For a time we lived in safety, but
	all is not as it once was, and our future here looks bleak ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	swamps are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The woods are teeming with
	grobolds and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hunter's Mark
<Hamlet_HuntersMarkIntro>
	Welcome, Traveler, to the hamlet Hunter's Mark. Six centuries
	ago, before ever Silverlance or even Knightsbridge was built,
	Argath the Hunter slew the Serpent of Tyrroth near this very
	spot. All days are darkened since the Turning -- if only
	Argath could return to protect us once more! The folk
	hereabouts need heroes ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	swamps are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The woods are teeming with
	grobolds and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Rogue's Market
<Hamlet_RoguesMarketIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to the Rogue's Market. I serve this hamlet
	as Runemaster. When the young Lord Truesteel in Knightsbridge
	exiled all his father's brutal henchmen, they took up an errant
	life of banditry in the Riverlands. Some of them came north to
	trade with the people of Swampstone, and this market sprung up
	to serve them. In these dark days, however, the bandits grow
	restless, and now all these lands are endangered ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	swamps are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The woods are teeming with
	grobolds and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Agan's Ring
<Hamlet_AgansRingIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to Agan's Ring! I am the Runemaster of this
	humble village. Ages ago the savage Gwendannen raised these
	stones, and traded here with the Lizardmen until Berren the
	Bold drove both Gwendannen and Scaly Ones away. He fought
	the final battle here, against the fierce lizard chieftain
	named Agan. Our folk have dwelt here since the Turning, but
	now new dangers overshadow all we have built ... \n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	swamps are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The woods are teeming with
	grobolds and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Saladan
<Hamlet_SaladanIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to the Village of Saladan!\n
	\n
	I am Drosten, and I serve as the Runemaster of this village.
	Gwendannen druids and raiders raised these stones untold
	ages ago, and dwelt here until Saladan the Templar came
	from Knightsbridge and conquered them fifty years ago. We
	have since prospered under the protection of Knightsbridge,
	but now all we have built is in peril.\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>


# Hamlet of Fort Troidan
<Hamlet_FortTroidanIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to Fort Troidan! I am Quinton, the
	Runemaster of this outpost. Brigands and sellswords, exiles
	from Knightsbridge, first raised these palisades, but
	Saladan the Templar took the fort in the name of Lord
	Truesteel of Knightsbridge, and it has served as a watchpost
	ever since. These are troubled times, and Lord Truesteel has
	more need of the fort than ever!\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>


# Hamlet of Arkten
<Hamlet_ArktenIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to Arkten. I an Rordin, the Runemaster of
	this hamlet. When the first lord of Knightsbridge came to
	Tyrranth at the head of an army of thugs and sellswords,
	many persecuted peasants hid themselves near the ancient
	cemetery here. The new Lord of Knightsbridge is just and
	fair, and now we live in the open. Though these are troubled
	times, and I wonder how much longer our people can stay ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Homlen's Grove
<Hamlet_HomlensGroveIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to Homlen's Grove. I am Archard, the
	Runemaster of this hamlet. For centuries, all the farmers of
	Tyrranth Minor have gathered here to sell livestock and
	produce to the people of Knightsbridge, but now the lands
	are laid waste and teeming with vile creatures, and the
	hamlet has withered. I know not if we can survive the perils
	of this age ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Tyver
<Hamlet_TyverIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to Tyver. I am Aylard, the Runemaster of
	this fair hamlet. Tyver was founded as a market for
	trade between the Safeholds of Knightsbridge and Silverlance,
	but now the roads have grown unsafe, and I fear the town's
	future is in peril ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Anomani Market Village
<Hamlet_AnomaniMarketIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to the Anomani Market. I am Aristle,
	Runemaster of this community. Thirty years ago, when the
	Centaurs built the Safehold of Silverlance, drifeters and
	wayward tinkers gathered here to sell goods to the new city.
	The market thrive to this day, though recent events cast a
	dark shaodow on all we have built here ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Justan's Rest
<Hamlet_JustansRestIntro>
	Welcome, Traveler, to the hamlet of Justan's Rest. I am
	Samworth, and I serve as Runemaster here. Justan was a
	mighty general of ages long gone, who defeated a legion of
	nomads not far from here. His tomb has long been lost, but
	legend has it that it lay near here. The times grow dark,
	and indeed we have need of heroes like Justan again ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Wainthorpe
<Hamlet_WainthorpeIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to Wainthorpe! I am Gerudin, the
	Runemaster of this village. For more than a thousand years,
	merchant wagons from distant lands stopped here on their way
	to Knightsbridge. All trade died at the Turning, and now new
	dangers threaten to overwhelm us ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Gwenmoot
<Hamlet_GwenmootIntro>
	Welcome, Traveller, to the village of Gwenmoot!  My name is
	Justen, and I am the Runemaster for this fair hamlet.
	Nestled here in the warm embrace of these ancient Gwendannen
	monoliths, Gwenmoot has stood for countless generations as a
	haven of tranquility in this dark and war-torn world.\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Calder
<Hamlet_CalderIntro>
	Welcome, traveler, to the village of Calder! I am Taggart,
	and serve as the Runemaster of this place. Calder is named
	for Calder the Pious, a great Prelate who singlehandedly
	thwarted an Orc invasion with his divine miracles. Calder
	left us more than ten years ago. A shame, really, for I fear
	we shall need his help again before long ...\n
	\n
	You should be wary and travel well armed, for these are
	dangerous times! Not only is our fair city having to remain
	ever viligant against the endless hordes of vermin, but our
	woods are filled with wicked creatures, and bandits plague
	the once-quiet river lands.  The swamps are teeming with
	ratmen and worse, and we've had reports of nightmarish
	visions near the ancient, mystical Runegate.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Kestamir (Dalgoth)
<Hamlet_KestamirIntro>
	Hail, traveler, and welcome! You stand now in the center of
	Kestamir, a new bastion against the troubles of this age.
	Only months ago, noble Centaurs from Therikos Senn built this
	place to help defend Wanford Castle from the foul folk and
	hideous beasts that dwell in the Outlands. Take rest here,
	provision yourselves, and then join the crusade!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Galmord (Dalgoth)
<Hamlet_GalmordIntro>
	Well met, stranger. Galmord was once this town's name, back
	before the Turning, when the world was broken and the Age of
	Strife was born. Once this was a thriving town, a stop for
	pilgrims on their way to Wanford or Dalgoth, but hordes of
	angry dead burned the place to the ground nearly a century
	ago. We're trying to rebuild, to start over, but now foul
	creatures and brigands are rising in the Outlands, and our
	new livelihoods are threatened. I hope you've come ready for
	battle ...\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hamlet of Kian Rill (Dalgoth)
<Hamlet_KianRillIntro>
	The roads have brought you to Kian Rill, traveler. Welcome!
	Long ago, when Aerynth was whole and Men still knew true
	death, this town served as a market for Wanford Castle and a
	waypoint for caravans bound for Dalgoth. The Turning has cut
	us off from other lands, and the old trade has withered away
	to nothing. Still, we still work and live here, protected by
	Wanford against the terrors that teem in the Outlands.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Fort Baelin (Dalgoth)
<Hamlet_FortBaelinIntro>
	Hail to thee! Welcome to Fort Baelin. The Crusaders in
	Wanford Castle raised these stockades after the Turning, and
	for years Baelin has served as their staging ground for
	incursions against the evil things that dwell in the
	Outlands. Recent months have been cruel, however, and the
	forces that once defended the fort have been called away. The
	last attacks have been hard indeed, as you can see. We need
	stout hearts and keen blades to keep up the defense. Are you
	up to the challenge?\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Valona (Dalgoth)
<Hamlet_ValonaIntro>
	Peace be with you. You have come to Valona, and you now walk
	on hallowed ground. For thousands of years the honored dead
	of Wanford Castle have been buried here, and the folk of
	Valona have tended their rest. But now times are worse. Dark
	forces are moving in the Outlands, and evil things seek to
	desecrate these graves. Will you help us defend them?\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hengest (Vorringia)
<Hamlet_HengestIntro>
	You stand in Hengest, stranger. Be welcome. Here Hengest the
	Heavy settled of old. This land was given him from Thane
	Stark in Starkholm, and to this day the peoples of this
	village are loyal to Starkholm. In times past we raised sheep
	and oxen, and brewed the finest mead known to any Northman!
	Alas, the winters have grown long and bleak, and the Dark
	Folk slaughter all our stock. Hunger has driven them down
	from the mountains, to linger at our doors like wolves. Arm
	yourself here, and go drive them back!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Valkirch (Vorringia)
<Hamlet_ValkirchIntro>
	Hail, stranger, and welcome to Valkirch! Once a great Church
	stood here, built to worship Vorrdan All-Father. A fat
	Southlander bishop raised it, and sought to draw the Thane
	in Starkholm to his flock. Ha! We Invorri are no sheep! The
	priest presumed too much, and now the bones of his church
	stand here, a reminder of the fury of the Northmen. A new
	church has risen up the road a ways, but we go not there. Take
	refuge and comfort here, but speak not of gods or liturgies!
	Here you shall be safe from the Dark Folk of the mountains.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Scraefahl (Vorringia)
<Hamlet_ScraefahlIntro>
	When the doom of Vorrdan All-Father shook the world and
	darkened the very sun, times grew dark in Uthgaard. The Dark
	Folk of the mountains came forth in hosts unknown since the
	time of Stark's landing, and all the outlying villages were
	burned, save this one. Here all the folk of Starkenvald stood
	as one, and the Karls of  Starkholm came to our aid. The Dark
	Folk were beaten back, and Scraefahl was made into a mighty
	fortress to shelter all should they ever come again. Alas,
	this winter is long, and I fear that need may soon be upon us
	all. In the mountains the Dark Folk are moving.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hrimdal (Vorringia)
<Hamlet_HrimdalIntro>
	Be welcome to the village of Hrimdal. Hrimdal Hartsbane was
	the mightiest henchmen of Stark the Sojourner, who conquered
	Uthgaard Isle long ago. Stark gave this vale to Hrimdal as a
	reward long ago, and a fine village still stands here, three
	hundred winters later. We have long prospered, but the winter
	grows grim indeed. Fell things stir even in our own lands
	now, and the Dark Folk of the mountains raid the Starkenvald
	again. Take your rest here, but be ready, for fell fiends
	draw close.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hothor's Doom (Vorringia)
<Hamlet_HothorsDoomIntro>
	Hothor is a name from legend, a mighty hero who long searched
	for Tharsir, the Thunderhammer of Herogar, Thane of Thanes.
	Long missing from Erkeng hold, Hothor's fate was unknown to
	his kinsmen. Stark son of Sarjek left hearth and home, and
	led a mighty host into the sea. Here they landed of old, and
	here they found their answer. You see now the bleached wreck
	of Hothor's ships. Alas, he was slain by the Dark Folk of the
	mountains. Stark buried Hothor's bones in Starkholm, and we
	have feuded with the Dark Folk ever since. Be welcome, and
	find more comfort here than Hothor did of old!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

######## Old World Outskirts Chapters

# "What vermin?  Is this town in danger?"
<VerminSilverlance>
	Hideous creatures!  Once the roads that wound through the
	outskirts of the Keep of Silverlance were peaceful, but no
	longer!  Giant ants and spiders creep up from the earth, and
	man-sized adders hide in the grass, ready to devour any who
	stray from the path. Be wary as you travel from one village
	to the next, for these creatures are strong.. and deadly!\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Outskirts of Silverlance is suitable for characters of
	level 1 to 3.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

<VerminKnightsbridge>
	Hideous creatures!  Once the roads that wound through the
	outskirts of Knightsbridge were peaceful, but no
	longer!  Giant ants and spiders creep up from the earth, and
	man-sized adders hide in the grass, ready to devour any who
	stray from the path. Be wary as you travel from one village
	to the next, for these creatures are strong.. and deadly!\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Outskirts of Knightsbridge is suitable for characters of
	level 1 to 3.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

<VerminSwampstone>
	Hideous creatures!  Once the roads that wound through the
	outskirts of Swampstone were peaceful, but no
	longer!  Giant ants and spiders creep up from the earth, and
	man-sized adders hide in the grass, ready to devour any who
	stray from the path. Be wary as you travel from one village
	to the next, for these creatures are strong.. and deadly!\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Outskirts of Swampstone is suitable for characters of
	level 1 to 3.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# "Tell me about the creatures in the north woods."
<WoodsSilverlance>
	It is true; last winter a tribe of small, wicked creatures
	came from the caverns and started to plague the Glen of
	Arangore, just north of these Outskirts.  Many say they are
	the servants of the great orcish host that attacked our town
	a generation ago.  The townsfolk call them 'grobolds,' and
	they are scornful, hideous little devils.  They've burned a
	number of farmers out of their homes, and one of the beasts,
	a particularly foul creature known as 'Reekor,' has even
	styled himself a king of their kind.  If only a hero would
	rise up, and seek out this Reekor, and punish him for his
	wicked ways...\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Glen of Arangore area is suitable for characters of
	level 3 through 10.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# "Tell me about the creatures in the east woods."
<WoodsKnightsbridge>
	It is true; last winter a tribe of small, wicked creatures
	came from the caverns and started to plague the Glen of
	Fethwick, just east of these Outskirts.  Many say they are
	the servants of the great orcish host that attacked our town
	a generation ago.  The townsfolk call them 'grobolds,' and
	they are scornful, hideous little devils.  They've burned a
	number of farmers out of their homes, and one of the beasts,
	a particularly foul creature known as 'Reekor,' has even
	styled himself a king of their kind.  If only a hero would
	rise up, and seek out this Reekor, and punish him for his
	wicked ways ...\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Glen of Fethwick area is suitable for characters of
	level 3 through 10.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# "Tell me about the creatures in the southeastern woods."
<WoodsSwampstone>
	It is true; last winter a tribe of small, wicked creatures
	came from the caverns and started to plague the Glen of
	Fethwick, far to the southeast of these Outskirts.  Many say they are
	the servants of the great orcish host that attacked our town
	a generation ago.  The townsfolk call them 'grobolds,' and
	they are scornful, hideous little devils.  They've burned a
	number of farmers out of their homes, and one of the beasts,
	a particularly foul creature known as 'Reekor,' has even
	styled himself a king of their kind.  If only a hero would
	rise up, and seek out this Reekor, and punish him for his
	wicked ways ...\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Glen of Fethwick area is suitable for characters of
	level 3 through 10.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# "Are the riverlands to the north safe area to travel?"
<RiverlandsKnightsbridge>
	Oh, no, my friend!  You do not want to go there!  The
	riverlands just north of these villages were once peaceful,
	but in recent time they have become nothing more than a
	haven for brigands, bandits and worse.  Only the very brave
	or very foolish should even think to venture there.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The riverlands area is suitable for characters of
	level 3 through 12.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# "Are the riverlands to the east a safe area to travel?"
<RiverlandsSilverlance>
	Oh, no, my friend!  You do not want to go there!  The
	riverlands just east of these villages were once peaceful,
	but in recent time they have become nothing more than a
	haven for brigands, bandits and worse.  Only the very brave
	or very foolish should even think to venture there.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The riverlands area is suitable for characters of
	level 3 through 12.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# "Are the riverlands to the south a safe area to travel?"
<RiverlandsSwampstone>
	Oh, no, my friend!  You do not want to go there!  The
	riverlands just south of these villages were once peaceful,
	but in recent time they have become nothing more than a
	haven for brigands, bandits and worse.  Only the very brave
	or very foolish should even think to venture there.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Lathgell Wetlands area is suitable for characters of
	level 3 through 12.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

"Are there really ratmen in the northeastern swamp?"
<SwampSilverlance>
	The swamp? A vile place! Though I have never actually seen one
	myself, I have heard the tales many times, caravans destined
	for the city of Knightsbridge have vanished into the mire,
	never to return.\n
	\n
	The creatures are said to live deep inside
	the Pen'shaar Bog, a swampland far to the northeast.
	The creatures call themselves the 'skrell'
	and the townsfolk say they have built themselves a city of
	roots, filth and garbage.  Heed my words, friend, and stay
	well clear of this place if you value your life.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The swamp area is suitable for characters of level 8
	through 18.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

"Are there really ratmen in the eastern swamp?"
<SwampKnightsbridge>
	The swamp? A vile place! Though I have never actually seen one
	myself, I have heard the tales many times, caravans destined
	for the city of Silverlance have vanished into the mire,
	never to return.\n
	\n
	The creatures are said to live deep inside
	the Pen'shaar Bog, a swampland far to the east -- well
	beyond the Forest of Arangore, halfway to the town of
	Silverlance.  The creatures call themselves the 'skrell' and
	the townsfolk say they have built themselves a city of
	roots, filth and garbage.  Heed my words, friend, and stay
	well clear of this place if you value your life.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Pen'shaar Bog area is suitable for characters of level 8
	through 18.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

"Are there really ratmen in the northern swamp?"
<SwampSwampstone>
	The swamp? A vile place! I have heard the tales many times, caravans
	 have vanished into the mire, never to return.\n
	\n
	The creatures are said to live deep inside
	the Nail-Tooth Fen, a swampland to the north. The creatures
	call themselves the 'skrell' and the townsfolk say they have
	built themselves a city of roots, filth and garbage. Heed
	my words, friend, and stay
	well clear of this place if you value your life.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Nail-Tooth Fen area is suitable for characters of level 8
	through 18.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>


"What can you tell me about Silverlance Keep?"
<CitySilverlance>
	Our village, like many others, is nestled in the quiet
	shadow of the bright and glorious city of centaurs!
	Silverlance Keep has stood since before the Turning, a
	stronghold of meditation and training in the arts of battle
	and magic.  There are merchants within the Keep who sell all
	manner of finely crafted goods, from spears and staves to
	hammers and shields.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

#"What can you tell me about the City of Knightsbridge?"
<CityKnightsbridge>
	The Lord of Knightsbridge is a true and just knight, gods be
	praised ... but his father never was. The last Lord was a
	petty warlord who ruled with an iron fist, surrounded by
	thugs and sellswords who bled the lord's taxes out of the
	innocent peasantry. His  son exiled these ruffians when he
	took the regency in Knightsbridge, driving them into the
	riverlands and marshes. They dwell there still, an army of
	brigands, waiting to take their vengeance on the innocent.\n
	\n
	Recently, our young lord has started repairing the walls of
	our fair city, and the influx of laborers has brought a
	number of fine merchants to the town.  If you are looking
	for training, or a good weapon and suit of mail, you would
	be well served to seek out the artisans in Knightsbridge.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

#"What can you tell me about the City of Swampstone?"
<CitySwampstone>
	These ruins are older than the Titans, older than the Sun --
	the Scaly Ones raised them in epochs long forgotten, even by
	the Gods. Berren the Bold broke the might of the Lizardmen
	centuries ago, before the Turning and the rise of the High
	King. Legends say that the Lizard men laid a cruse upon
	these ruins when they left them, and indeed all Berren's
	line all died ignoble deaths long ago. The ruins were shunned
	until after the Turning, when need drove outcasts and
	unfortunates from distant fragments to take refuge here. We
	are far from prosperous, but here we live free of any lord
	or temple. The swamps grow more dangerous of late, however,
	and I wonder if the Scaly Curse may not yet befall us --
	we have dire need of heroes!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

#"What is this Runegate, and where does it lead?"
<RunegateSilverlance>
	An ancient and mysterious structure, many believe that the
	Runegates predate even the Elves.  Very few know their
	workings, and even those who devote a lifetime to their
	study are still baffled by their hidden mysteries.  To the
	initiated, Runegates provide a means of travel, allowing one
	to cover vast distances in the mere blink of an eye.\n
	\n
	Our townfolk call the nearest runegate Goland's Ring, named
	for the old fool Goland who wandered into the gate chasing a
	lost sheep.  He returned to us the following season, a
	wasting sickness upon him and a madness in his eyes.  In his
	sickness, he raved about an island of the walking dead, and
	a swamp filled with lizards who walk like men. Since that
	day, we have stayed clear of that strange ruin ... and so
	should you, if you value your sanity!\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Forest Incounnu is suitable for characters of level 11
	to 20.\n
	The Haroun Wildlands are suitable for characters of level 11
	to 20.\n
	The Ratkell Swamp is suitable for characters of level 18 to
	27.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

#"What is this Runegate, and where does it lead?"
<RunegateKnightsbridge>
	An ancient and mysterious structure, many believe that the
	Runegates predate even the Elves. Very few know their
	workings, and even those who devote a lifetime to their
	study are still baffled by their hidden mysteries.  To the
	initiated, Runegates provide a means of travel, allowing one
	to cover vast distances in the mere blink of an eye.\n
	\n
	Our townfolk call the runegate Shimmergate, named for the
	eerie effect that the lights of the gate give off in the
	darkest of hours. Many say that strange shadows can be seen
	through the passages of fire, tales of the walking dead and
	of twisted serpentine creatures who dance in a mockery of
	human form. Most of us stay clear of this place -- for it is
	clearly dangerous, and evil!\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Forest Incounnu is suitable for characters of level 11
	to 20.\n
	The Haroun Wildlands are suitable for characters of level 11
	to 20.\n
	The Ratkell Swamp is suitable for characters of level 18 to
	27.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

#"What is this Runegate, and where does it lead?"
<RunegateSwampstone>
	An ancient and mysterious structure, many believe that the
	Runegates predate even the Elves. Very few know their
	workings, and even those who devote a lifetime to their
	study are still baffled by their hidden mysteries.  To the
	initiated, Runegates provide a means of travel, allowing one
	to cover vast distances in the mere blink of an eye.\n
	\n
	Our townfolk call the runegate Shimmergate, named for the
	eerie effect that the lights of the gate give off in the
	darkest of hours. Many say that strange shadows can be seen
	through the passages of fire, tales of the walking dead and
	of twisted serpentine creatures who dance in a mockery of
	human form. Most of us stay clear of this place -- for it is
	clearly dangerous, and evil!\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The Forest Incounnu is suitable for characters of level 11
	to 20.\n
	The Haroun Wildlands are suitable for characters of level 11
	to 20.\n
	The Ratkell Swamp is suitable for characters of level 18 to
	27.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

#"I wish to start my own guild, and eventually create a City.  How might I do so?"
<RunemasterGuild>
	Aha!  You are interested in starting a guild, or founding a
	city?  Well, my friend, in that case I may be of service.  I
	can sell you the items that you will need.\n
	\n
	There are over a dozen different Guild themes to choose from,
	from Noble House to Mercenary Company, War Temple to
	Wizard's Conclave. Once you have a charter, you may use it
	to select your coat of arms and motto.\n
	\n
	A word of warning, however - using these charters will mean
	breaking your oath of fealty to the local lords!  This will
	result in banishment to the mainland for you and all your
	guildmates.  Do not attempt this until your guild is ready!\n
	\n
	I also sell Inns, Builders, Stewards and Guild seeds, which
	can be use on the mainland to found a new City.\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The continents of Tyrannth Major, Khar Thale and Stormvald
	are suitable for characters level 20 and higher.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# "Can I leave this village?  How can I  reach the mainland?"
<RunemasterContinent>
	If you wish to leave this village, I can easily repledge you
	to another.  A word of caution, however -- the continent is
	a dangerous place!  Those who are inexperienced should stay
	pledged to one of the starting hamlets.\n
	\n
	For more experienced adventurers, I can also repledge you to
	a city in the mainland ... but be careful, the continents do
	not benefit from the protection of our local lords, and can
	be quite fatal for the inexperienced traveller!\n
	\n
	^\c086203089The continent of Tyrannth Minor is suitable for characters
	of level 1 through 20.\n
	The continents of Tyrannth Major, Khar Thale and Stormvald
	are suitable for characters level 20 and higher.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Dalgoth Outlands (Dalgoth)
# "Where can I help the fight?"
<RunemasterOutlands>
	Beware the Outlands, good traveler! The grace of the
	All-Father and his servants have kept the Wanford outskirts
	relatively calm, but if you leave them you shall surely face
	deadly peril. Swarms of Grobolds dwell to the east, thirsting
	for destruction. To the west foul bandits and brigands have
	encamped themselves in the broken riverlands, scheming to
	overthrow Wanford.\n
	\n
	But even these are trifles compared to the beasts that dwell
	to the north, across the narrow straits! Hideous vermin and
	ratmen lurk in a foul swamp, and the wilderness to the north
	is filled with savage beastmen and Aelfborn who attack any
	intruders! Verily I say to you, if you doubt your courage or
	your strength, venture not to the north! Too many who walk
	that way return here after their deaths ...\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Dalgoth City (Dalgoth)
# "What can you tell me about Wanford?"
<CityWanford>
	All these lands stand under the patronage of Wanford Castle,
	ancient stronghold of the Holy Church. Centuries ago the
	great Prelates of Men, Elves, and Centaurs all convened there
	to compose the Wanford Creed, cornerstone of the Holy Church.
	The city has witnessed countless wars, disasters, and
	hardships, but her stout walls still stand. You can find
	supplies and arms in plenty there, as well as able folk who
	can guide and instruct adventurers.\n
	\n
	The Turning sunk all the lands around, leaving the city on a
	broken isle far from Dalgoth and aid. These are troubling
	times, but the Bishop in Wanford still has faith, and the
	grace of its masters will preserve it even through these
	hardships.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Dalgoth Repledge Message
# "I'd like to leave."
<RunemasterRepledge>
	If you wish to leave this village, I can easily repledge you
	to another, or to one of the Safeholds on the mainland if
	you've grown strong enough. A word of caution, however -- the
	mainland is a dangerous place. Those who are inexperienced
	should only move from one starting village to another. Where
	would you go?\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Vorringia Mob Info
# "Say more of these Dark Folk in the Mountains."
<RunemasterDarkFolk>
	Aye, the Dark Folk came here long ago, born of Chaos.
	The Nibolgr lead them, those the Southlanders name Orcs,
	but their lesser cousins the Goblins and Grobolds are with
	them, the wretches we Invorri call Pukjet and Huldr. They
	have burrowed into the Garstaark peaks like maggots and
	grown so many that the Huldrings now haunt our lands,
	looking for plunder. In years past our steel and
	fire kept them at bay, but since the Turning matters are
	worse. Have you the strength to match them?\n
	\n
	^\c086203089View your world map by pressing M.^\c086203089\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Vorringia City
# "Say more of Starkholm."
<CityStarkholm>
	Stark, Sarjek's son led the Invorri to this island long ago,
	seeking Hothor, his long lost kinsman. The fury of sea and
	storm smashed all our ships, but we do not miss the lands of
	Vorringheim, for here the Clan of the Starks have ruled as
	thanes for three hundred winters. Starkholm is a mighty city,
	raised by Stark and his sons. If you find our village
	lacking, there may be more in Starkholm's halls and markets
	to catch your eye.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Vorringia Repledge
# "How can I leave this village?"
<VorringiaRepledge>
	So the wide world beckons, eh? I can tie your soul to the
	heartstone of any of the villages in the Starklands, or to
	Starkholm itself. If you are truly bold, I can also send you
	to Erkeng Hold in Vorringheim or Aeldreth in the greener
	lands to the south. But be warned: our isle may have its
	troubles, but on the mainland a man always walks in danger,
	and death is never far behind him. Go not there lest ye have
	the strength for it! So, where would you go then, stranger?\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>