# ------------------------------------------------ #
# Dialog file for dealing with Vendors and Guards  #
# ------------------------------------------------ #

##### Hostile
<HostileIntro>
	I've been instructed not to deal with the likes of you,
	knave.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

##### Vendors

# Animal Trainer
<VendorAnimalTrainer>
	No one need walk alone in these dangerous times! I have wild
	beasts broken and trained, or even monsters spellbound to serve.
	Buy any of my beasts, and they'll serve you well.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Armorer
<VendorArmorer>
	We all return from death in this black age, but the knives
	still bite us, yes? Armor I have to stop any edge or point.
	I'll buy found armor, sell you new armor, or repair suits that
	have seen one fight too many.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Builder
<VendorBuilder>
	So much in this world has been destroyed, how much better to
	create! I can draft the plans and assemble the materials for
	any feudal structure you desire.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Builder - Elf
<VendorBuilder_Elf>
	Once the mighty towers of spires of the Deathless Empire rose
	like forests of crystal and alabaster, touching the clouds!
	I know much of the ancient ways, and can weave palaces worthy
	of the Highborn, building cities that recall our vanished
	glories.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Builder - Invorri
<VendorBuilder_Invorri>
	What good are the coffins of the South here in Frykka's lands,
	where the bite of winter can break the very stones? Torvald's
	children have always known how to build for winter. I am
	Invorri, great in craft, and will raise strong halls for you.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Builder - Irekei
<VendorBuilder_Irekei>
	For countless years the Irekei have lived in tents made to
	capture breeze and shade. I know the secrets of their making,
	and can craft you a city that would be the envy of the
	wealthiest virakt.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Bursar
<VendorBursar>
	I see that you have not come to pray. Very well. I can keep
	your belongings safe in my vault, and give you vouchers that
	will let you collect them again in distant cities.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Innkeeper
<VendorInnkeeper>
	Welcome, wayward soul! For a bit of coin you can take your
	rest here, in peace or war.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Runemaster
<VendorRunemaster>
	I am a Runemaster, and yon Tree of Life is my charge. If you
	wish to found a Guild, build a City, I can sell all that
	you'll need. If you would pledge yourself to this Tree or
	another, I can help you.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Sage
<VendorSage>
	The mystic arts are not forgotten here, good patron! Mystic
	talismans, powerful scrolls, and magical trinkets I have to
	sell, and will gladly buy any you might carry.\n
	\n
	I can craft siege staves, but such things are not for sale! I
	will only place such dangerous things in my master's hands.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Steward
<VendorSteward>
	Do you seek to build a shop, or a city? I know hundreds of
	craftsmen, artisans, laborers and soldiers. For a price, I'll
	find you any tradesman you might need.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Tailor (Seamstress)
<VendorTailor>
	Who says all art has died in this dark age? I have fine
	garments from distant lands to sell, and will buy any that you
	carry!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Weaponsmith (all but hammersmith)
<VendorWeaponsmith>
	Once we smiths forged plowshares, but now there is only call
	for weapons. Whether you look to buy, sell, or repair a weapon,
	you've come to the right place.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Hammersmith
<VendorHammersmith>
	Once we smiths forged plowshares, but now there is only call
	for weapons. Whether you look to buy, sell, or repair a weapon,
	you've come to the right place.\n
	\n
	I can craft siege hammers, but such things are not for sale! I
	will only place such dangerous things in my master's hands.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Siege Engineer
<VendorSiegeEngineer>
	Is it to be war, then? You've come to the right place -- for
	onslaught or defense, I can supply everything an army needs.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Artillery Captain
<VendorArtilleryCaptain>
	Yes sir! Is the word given? If you need siege engines, I'll
	have them ready in no time at all!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Bowyer
<VendorBowyer>
	Only a fool stakes his life on a blade -- why look a foe in
	the eye when you can slay him from a quarter mile away? I've
	bows and crossbows to sell from every corner of Aerynth.\n
	\n
	I can craft siege bows, but such things are not for sale! I
	will only place such dangerous things in my master's hands.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Helmsmith
<VendorHelmsmith>
	In these dark times we all need hard heads and thick skulls
	to survive, but is that enough? No! Place a helm upon your
	noble brow, and keep your brains where they belong!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Shieldsmith
<VendorShieldsmith>
	One can never be too careful in these times of strife and
	chaos. The best defense of all is never to be struck -- put
	a shield upon your arm, and keep you foes' weapons far away.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Vaultkeeper
<VendorVaultkeeper>
	Tired of giving your valuables over to corrupt Bankers? My 
	vault's safe as any Church, but the service here's even 
	better: I'll release your goods to all your kin, letting 
	you share your wealth among all your characters! What do 
	you say?\n\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Gambler
<VendorGambler>
	Do you feel lucky? Saedron, the Silver Goddess, wove the 
	tapestry of your destiny before time ever began. But she 
	also forged your luck. Will you play a game of chance? 
	Come buy: for a pittance, I'll sell you one of Saedron's 
	gifts. Choose your box well: it could be a lump of coal, or
	it could be an artifact beyond price. You cannot know until 
	you open it.  The more you buy, the better your chances -- 
	runestones from the Cliffs of Fate, weapons, deeds, all of 
	these and more may be in these gifts ... or they may not. 
	If you find you do not luck your gifts, come back later 
	-- my stock is like the face of the Silver Moon: it always 
	changes.  Mighty gifts will appear here later, and gifts 
	here now may vanish tomorrow. Do you feel lucky? Shall we 
	see if Saedron favors you?
<CHAPTEREND>

##### Guards

# Guard Captain
<GuardGuardCaptain>
	Hail! If you worry to the security of your City, just say the
	word, and I'll train fine guardsmen for you. It's not cheap to
	maintain a militia, though ... \n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Magister
<GuardMagister>
	I'm a Wizard, mind you, and an able teacher. Would you have
	spell-flingers to protect your city? The training is an easy
	matter, though expensive ...\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Guard
<GuardGuard>
	What's all this, then? If you've no trouble to warn me of, be
	off!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Wall Archer
<GuardWallArcher>
	Away with ye, I'm busy defending this fair city!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Archer
<GuardArcher>
	Ho there, stranger. I've got my eye on you.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Adept
<GuardAdept>
	If you've no danger to report, pray do not interrupt my rounds.\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Seneschal
<VendorSeneschal>
	Need you the fruits of the guild's mines?  I can show you
	what the workers have gathered.\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Harvester
<VendorHarvester>
	Away with ye, I've no energy for talking.\n
<CHAPTEREND>

# Alchemist
<VendorAlchemist>
	Troubled by the travails of life? Antagonized by 
	ailments, agonies, or aches? Do you find your 
	performance in battle ... less than satisfying? Here 
	is the cure! Tinctures, elixirs, essences and 
	essential saltes; Experience better living through 
	Alchemy! Yes, alchemy; the art of the ancients, and 
	now the science of the future!\n
	\n
	The Brotherhood of Alchemists (an affiliate of the 
	Brotherhood of Transcendence) have combined modern 
	ingredients with ancient wisdom to create potions to 
	improve every aspect of existence! Good health, 
	mystic power, the serpent's speed, or the hare's 
	swiftness; here you will find them all, refined, 
	sublimed, calcified, amalgamated, and distilled into 
	a bottle. Proven safe in ... dozens of laboratory 
	experiments! Straight from the crucible to you -- 
	certified pure and efficacious by the High Conclave 
	of Wizardry. Or they will be. Soon. Very soon, as 
	sure as the approval hearings end. You know those 
	wizards ... But enough digression! Act while the 
	athannor is hot, and improve your life now! Come buy, 
	come buy!\n
	\n
	But do take care -- these potions are precious, and 
	make tasty targets for thieves and marauders. All the 
	more reason to use them quickly! Drink up!\n
	\n
<CHAPTEREND>